Guide to the Tillie Olsen Papers, 1930-1990 M0667
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Tillie Olsen papers
1930-1990
M0667
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
62.0 Linear feet ca. 62 linear ft.
The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, literary manuscripts by American author Tillie Olsen and others, material on the Longshoremen's Strike and the Socialist Party from during the mid-1930s, teaching material and student work, clippings, pamphlets, book reviews, awards, etc. Accessions from 2009 including photographs have also been processed.
Olsen, Tillie
Biography
Tillie Olsen was born in Nebraska in 1913 and has lived in San Francisco for most of her life. Her education was cut short by the Depression: she wrote and published when young, but the necessity of raising and supporting four children and full-time work prevented her from writing for twenty years. She was in her mid-forties before she began again. Tell Me A Riddle was originally published in 1962, and its title novella received the O. Henry Award as the best American story of 1961. In 1974, forty years after part of its chapter appeared in an early Partisan Review, her 'lost' novel, Yonnondio: From the Thirties, was published. Tillie Olsen has taught at Amherst College, Stanford University, was Writer-in-Residence at Massachustts Institute of Technology, Distinguished Visiting Professor at the University of Massachusetts in Boston, and a Fellow of the Radcliffe Institute. She has received both a Ford Foundation and National Endowment for the Arts grants, a Guggenheim Fellowship, and an Award for Distinguished Contribution to American Literature from the American Academy and the National Institute of Arts and Letters. Her first work of non-fiction, Silences, was published in 1979.
Provenance
Purchased, 1993, 1994, 1995, and 1998.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Aberlin, Betty.; Appleton, Sarah.; Atwood, Margaret Eleanor, 1939-; Bacon, Ernst, 1898-1990; Ballantyne, Sheila.; Barolini, Helen, 1925-; Bingham, Sallie.; Boucher, Sandy; Boyde, Blanche; Boyle, Kay, 1902-1992; Boynton, Grace.; Brandon, Dolores.; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Brindel, June Rachuy.; Brodine, Karen.; Brown, Rosellen.; Bryant, Dorothy, 1930-; Cahill, Susan Neunzig.; Childress, Alice.; Cliff, Michelle.; Coiner, Constance.; Conroy, Lynne.; Cooper, Jane, 1924-; Cowley, Malcolm.; Cumming, Patricia.; Cuomo, Joe.; De Ford, Miriam Allen, 1888-1975.; DeSalvo, Louise A., 1942-; Duncan, Erika; DuPlessis, Rachel Blau.; Durham, Flora.; Earle, Ralph.; Elman, Richard M.; English, Dierdre.; Ettinger, Elzbieta.; Fisher, Elizabeth.; Foley, Margaret.; Gerson, Deborah.; Gilbert, Celia, 1932-; Gilgun, John.; Goedicke, Patricia.; Goldfarb, Sidney, 1942-; Gottlieb, Annie.; Green, Hannah, 1932-; Greenberg, Joanne.; Griffin, Susan.; Grumbach, Doris.; Guérard, Albert J. (Albert Joseph), 1914-; Hedges, Elaine.; Heffernan, Helen.; Henry, Dewitt.; Homley, Elaine.; Hopkins, Glen; Hughes, Mary Gray; Janows, Jill.; Jong, Erica; Kallet, Marilyn.; Kaye/Kantrowitz, Melanie.; Keeble, John, 1944-; Kitrilakis, Thalia.; Kizer, Carolyn.; Klepfisz, Irena, 1941-; Kolodny, Annette, 1941-; Konecky, Edith; Krapf, Norbert.; Kumin, Maxine, 1925-; Lawrence, Margaret.; Lazreg, Marnia.; LeGuin, Ursula, 1929-; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Lewis, Janet, 1899-1998; Limmer, Ruth, 1923-; MacDowell Art Colony.; Mackenzie, Midge.; MacShane, Frank.; Malamud, Bernard.; Meehan, Maude.; Meyer, Howard N.; Meyer, Odette.; Miller, Nolan, 1912-; Millet, Kate.; Miner, Valerie.; Minty, Judith, 1937-; Mirrielees, Edith R., (Edith Ronald), 1878-1962.; Moers, Ellen, 1928-; Moffat, Mary Jane; Morgan, Ellen.; Moss, Rose; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Murray, Michele.; Myers, Margaret, 1947-; Naiman, Adeline.; Nason, Thelma Campbell.; Ng, Fae Myenne, 1956-; Orr, Elaine Neil.; Ozick, Cynthia.; Paley, Grace.; Papanek, Hanna.; Park-Fuller, Linda Marguerite.; Phillips, Jayne Anne, 1952-; Piercy, Marge; Polite, Frank.; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980.; Radcliffe Institute.; Randall, Margaret, 1936-; Redman, Blanche.; Reeves, Nancy, 1913-; Rich, Adrienne Cecile; Roemer, Michael, 1928-; Rogers, Linda.; Rosen, Norma.; Rosenfelt, Deborah Silverton.; Ruddick, Sally.; Russ, Joanne.; Sarton, May, 1912-; Saxton, Ruth.; Schick, Carla.; Scowcroft, Richard; Sexton, Anne, 1928-1974; Seyersted, Per, 1921-; Shameless Hussy Press.; Shanahan, Thomazine.; Showalter, Elaine; Smith, Alice.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Starkman, Elaine Markus.; Sternburg, Janet.; Stone, Ruth.; Swan, Barbara.; Sweeney, John.; Tanenhaus, Beverly.; Tovish, Margo.; Turow, Scott; Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977; Walker, Alice, 1944-; Ward, Theadora.; Washington, Mary Helen.; Waterman, Ray.; Wilder, Annie.; Wilson, J.J., 1936-; Wong, Nellie.; Wright, Michael.; Yalom, Marilyn; Yamada, Mitsuye.; Zucker, Jack.; American literature--20th century.; Longshoremen's Strike--United States.
- Series 1. Manuscripts
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I is comprised of her manuscripts and related material. This includes the original drafts from Tell Me a Riddle, Yonnondio: From the Thirties, Silences, Requa, and other miscellaneous publications in both magazines and newspapers. Also included are galleys, typescripts, corrections to texts, adaptations, translations, reviews and various stage production scripts. [The listing often makes reference to the word "makings" which was Tillie Olsen's designation for her own notes and writings for the particular text.]
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Baptism" ("Oh, Yes") (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Baptism" ("Oh, Yes") (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Baptism" ("Oh, Yes") (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Oh, Yes" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, typescript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, originals/revisions (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tell Me a Riddle (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, typescript (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, galley (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" and "Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, Seeds of "Oh, Yes" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, "I Stand Here Ironing" (makings) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "I Stand Here Ironing": Engl. 103.1 story, includes comments (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, makings, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, corrections (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, proof (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Hey Sailor, What Ship?" - reference: "My Last Farewell" by Jose Rizal (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Tell Me a Riddle: Czechoslovakian translation (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, Peoples Republic of China translation (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Notes: "Tell Me A Riddle" film (for cinemetographer) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Tell Me a Riddle": screenplay/stage production (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Tell Me a Riddle": stage adaptation by Bobbi Ausubel (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Hey Sailor, What Ship?": teleplay by C.R. Portz, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Tell Me a Riddle: A Point of View Analysis of the Film vs. the Fiction" (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Tell Me a Riddle": screenplay by Joyce Eliason, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, A rough draft of an adaptation, by Ann Weinstein (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Reviews and announcements of productions: Tell Me a Riddle (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tell Me a Riddle: Midge Mackenzie film and related (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, book cover and introduction (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reviews, Tell Me a Riddle (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reviews, Tell Me a Riddle (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Review, Tell Me a Riddle, by Dorothy Parker (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Yonnondio, makings (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Yonnondio, makings (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Yonnondio, makings (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yonnondio, makings (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Final revisions, Yonnondio (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence re. publication (incl. Hanna Green) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Yonnondio, galley (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Yonnondio, galley (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Yonnondio: theater adaptation, 1986 (University of California, Santa Barbara) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Yonnondio: screenplay by Martin W. Nicholson and Kenneth Fink, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Yonnondio: screenplay by Martin W. Nicholson, 1984 (title page - p. 66) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Yonnondio: screenplay by Martin W. Nicholson, 1984, (p.67 - 135) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Yonnondio: Russian translation (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Ozarks Arts Interpretation Festival: Yonnondio Productions (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Reviews: Yonnondio (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Reviews: Yonnondio (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reviews: Yonnondio (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: sources, includes The Nation (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rebecca Harding Davis: Her Life and Times: makings (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Silences, master set (title page - p.100) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Silences, (pp. 101 - 201) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Silences, (pp. 202 - 301) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Silences, (pp. 302 - 375) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Silences, galley (title page - p. 25 and miscellaneous) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Silences, galley (pp. 26 - 50) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Silences, galley (pp. 51 - 100) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Silences, galley (pp. 101 - 142) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Silences, galley (pp. 143 - 179) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Figures for "One Out of Twelve" (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Figures for "One out of Twelve" (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Silences, "One Out of Twelve" makings (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sources for Silences (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Silences, galley (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Silences, galley (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Silences, makings (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Silences, makings (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Silences, makings (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Silences, makings (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Silences, galley (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Silences, typescript/makings (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Silences, corrections (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Silences, galley/corrections (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Silences, typescript/makings (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Silences, galley and corrections (One Out of Twelve) (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Silences, corrections (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Silences, typescript with corrections (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Silences, galley (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Silences, galley and corrections (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Silences, "Life in the Iron Mills": galley (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Silences, "Life in the Iron Mills": galley (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Silences, "Life in the Iron Mills": galley (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Silences, "Life in the Iron Mills": galley (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Silences, unsorted (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Silences, Hardy, Thomas - drafts, notes (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Silences, Melville, Herman - afternotes (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Silences, Cather, Willa - drafts, notes (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Silences, Davis, Rebecca Harding (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Silences, Baudelaire (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Silences, "One Out of Twelve" - the figures, drafts (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Silences, Blake, William (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Silences, Hopkins, Gerald Manley - notes (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Silences, Women Who are Writers - drafts (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Silences, Women Who are Writers - drafts (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Silences, "One Out of Twelve" - drafts (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Silences, "One Out of Twelve" - drafts (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Silences, "One Out of Twelve" - Mss (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Silences, drafts (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Intro/Dedication to Silences - drafts (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Silences, galleys with corrections (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Silences, galleys with corrections (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Life in the Iron Mills or the Korl Woman" by Rebecca Harding Davis with galleys of Biographical Interpretation by Tillie Olsen (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Silences, galley (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Silences, "Writers Who are Women in Our Time" - typescript and College edition, Oct. 1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Silences, subject index (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Silences, miscellaneous information, articles, quotations, and outgoing correspondence (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Silences, makings (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Silences, typescript (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Silences, corrections (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Silences, article, Harper's Magazine, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Silences, Sources - Authors and Friends, 1897; Selection of letters from Miss Jewsbury to Jane Welsh Carlyle (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "Women Who Writers in Our Century: One Out of Twelve" - College edition, 1972. (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Reprints of Silences (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Silences, galley (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Silences, galley (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Silences, galley (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Silences, galley (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Silences, articles (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "Conversations with Tillie Olsen," re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Conversations with Tillie Olsen," re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Notes re. Silences (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Silences, Publication files (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Requa, makings (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Requa, typescript (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Requa, galley (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Requa, typescript (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "The Word Made Flesh": makings (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "The Word Made Flesh": makings (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "The Word Made Flesh": makings (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - "The Word Made Flesh", typescript and xerox (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - "The Word Made Flesh", published (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - "The Word Made Flesh", correspondence (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "My Mother's Dying Vision" or "A Dream Vision": makings (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - "My Mother's Dying Vision" or "A Dream Vision": makings (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - "My Mother's Dying Vision" or "A Dream Vision", typescript (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified manuscript (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother: correspondence (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, notes, corrections, correspondence (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, excerpts (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, correspondence, exhibition checklist (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, xerox of photographs (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, xerox of photographs (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, xerox of photographs (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, xerox of photographs (and captions) (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, makings (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, makings (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, typescript (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, text and corrections, with correspondence (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, text and corrections (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, galley (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, reviews, articles (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, contents listing (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Mother to Daughter, Daughter to Mother, Preface; "Motheroath" by Julie Olsen Edwards (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - A Woman Reader: proposal (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - A Woman Reader: proposal (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - First Drafts, Last Drafts: exhibit writings (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - First Drafts, Last Drafts: exhibit writings (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - "Lost Women": makings (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - "Thousand-Dollar Vagrant," as published in The New Republic, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - "The Strike" (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - "Fuzzy" or "Not for You I Weep" (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - "Fuzzy" or "Not for You I Weep", for First Words (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - "Fuzzy" or "Not for You I Weep", "Not for You I Weep" - original typescript (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "Fuzzy" or "Not for You I Weep", original typescript and notes (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - First Words, xerox of Olsen's contribution (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Stories: "A Mother," "A Diseased Story" or "Davey" (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Poem: "The Stalking" (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "I Want You Women Up North to Know," 1934 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - "The Realist" (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - "Shadows Waiting," "The Strike" ca. 1930-32 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - "Franklin, Champion of Freedom" (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - "Momma's Revolt" (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - "Why They're Trying Don" (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - "Help Her to Believe" - first publication of "Ironings": title page only (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Tell Me a Riddle, oversized galley, 1961 (Box 3)
- Series 2. Papers, 1930-1950
  Series II consists of material from 1930-1950, and this series is divided into two distinct parts. Series IIa, the first part, contains Tillie Olsen's personal writings from this time period, which include partial stories, verse, journal entries, and newspaper articles. Reference is made in this series to Olsen's involvement with the Socialist Party and the Longshoreman's Strike during the mid 1930's. This series ends with all her bound journals and notebooks, the majority of which she wrote in high school. Series IIb, also from the time period 1930-1950, contains newsclippings, pamphlets, and bulletins which pertain to the Longshoreman's Strike and various other Strike issues. There is reference to Tillie Olsen's prison sentence in the mid-1930's and an FBI file kept on Tillie Olsen until 1944. Finally, there is a collection of manuscripts which includes poems and stories written by various individuals other than Tillie Olsen during the 1930's, some of which were written by Jeannette Gray.
  - Subseries A. Miscellaneous Early Writings (incl. journals, etc.), circa 1930-1950's
    - Adolescent writings and notes (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Adolescent writings and notes, and journal entries (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Adolescent writings and notes, and journal entries (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified fragments: high school (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - High school: verse (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - High school: verse (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - High school: verse (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - High school: verse (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's, High school (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's, High school (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's, High school (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Journal entries, notes: 1930's - 40's, High school (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Journal entries, notes: age 16, 17, 18 - High school: Faribault and some San Francisco (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Fragment: "Arne" (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938-39 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Stockton, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      account (story) of an abortion
    - Potential stories: abortion (?) and Imperial Valley (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Notes: Socialist Party (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Notes, clippings re. longshoreman's strike (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Outline for speech, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Notes:, 1930's - 50's (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Stanford Time (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Stanford Time, from notebook, 1955-56 (Box 16, Folder 20)